Register of the Sergei Aleksandrovich Golovan Papers, 1919-1921
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei Aleksandrovich Golovan Papers,
1919-1921
28005
Golovan, Sergei Aleksandrovich
8 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (3.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, military orders, communiqués, and clippings, relating to the Russian Civil War, and White Russian military relations with Switzerland.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Switzerland.; Military attachés.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains material from the office of Maj.-Gen. Sergei Golovan, head of the Rossiiskaia Voennaia Agentura v Shveitsarii (Russian Military Agency in Switzerland). It covers the period 1919-1921 and includes correspondence, orders, and operational, political and intelligence reports received from various White Russian offices and officials, including the headquarters of the Vooruzhennyia Sily Iuga Rossii (VSIUR) (Armed Forces of South Russia) and the Voennyi Predstavitel' Verkhovnago Pravitelia pri Soiuznykh Pravitel'stvakh I Soiuznom Verkhovnom Komandovanii (Military Representative of the Supreme Ruler to the Allied Governments and Allied Supreme Command). Most of this material is related to Russian military personnel residing or passing through Switzerland and especially to sick and invalid former prisoners of war in Swiss sanatoria.
Also included are proclamations and other official publications of VSIUR and a collection of clippings from the Russian, Swiss, and British press.
This collection was first arranged by Lieut.-Gen. Nikolai Golovin and the present register fully retains this arrangement, in which the material is divided numerically into files.
Series Description
- ROSSIISKAIA VOENNAIA AGENTURA V SHVEITSARII, 1919-1920., Boxes 1-8
  Correspondence with various White Russian offices and officials, especially the office of Gen. Dmitrii Shcherbachev in Paris and the headquarters of VSIUR (Vooruzhennyia Sily Iuga Rossii), orders, reports, information bulletins, miscellaneous material re military personnel and former Russian prisoners of war residing in Switzerland, bound clippings from Swiss, English, and Russian press. Arranged by file number and therein by physical form
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1919-1920., Box 9
  Proclamations under the signature of Gen. Aleksei Denikin and reports of VSIUR General Staff
Container List
- ROSSIISKAIA VOENNAIA AGENTURA V SHVEITSARII, 1919-1920
  - File 1. Orders and official operational, political, and intelligence reports received by the Rossiiskaia Voennaia Agentura v SHveitsarii from General D. Shcherbachev, Voennyi Predstavitel' Verkhovnago Pravitelia pri Soiuznykh Pravitel'stvakh I Soiuznom Verkhovnom Komandovanii, 1919
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Orders, 1919 September-November (Folder 2)
    - Reports, 1919
      - October (Folder 3)
      - November (Folder 4-5)
      - December (Folder 6)
    - Telegrams, 1919 October-November (Folder 7)
  - File 2. Miscellaneous orders received from Voennyi Predstavitel' Glavnokomanduiushchago Russkoi Armii Pri Pravitel'stve Frantsuzskoi Respubliki, 1920 (Folder 8)
  - File 3. Printed information bulletins issued by the Omsk Government re military matters and relations with foreign governments, 1919 (Folder 9)
  - File 4. News bulletins issued by the Biuro Russkoi Pechati v Konstantinopole, 1921 (Folder 10)
  - File 5. Orders and correspondence re recruitment of military personnel for White Armies, 1919-1920 (Folder 11-13)
  - File 6. Russian military personnel in Switzerland, 1919-1920
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Folder 14)
    - Alphabetical listing of resident military personnel (Folder 15)
    - Correspondence re military personnel in Switzerland (Folder 16-18)
  - File 7. Miscellaneous office correspondence with other Russian military missions, institutions, and organizations, especially re military personnel, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - File 8. Same as above, 1919-1920 (Folder 5-6)
  - File 9. Correspondence with General D. Shcherbachev, Lieut.-General Nikolai Monkevich, Glavnoupolnomochennyi Glavnokomanduiushchago Vooruzhennymi Silami Iuga Rossii, and other military missions, mostly re recruitment of military personnel, 1919-1920 (Folder 7-8)
  - File 10
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Folder 9)
    - General. Official orders of VSIUR headquarters and reports of Otdel Propagandy Pri VSIUR (Folder 10)
    - News bulletins, Biuro Russkoi Pechati v Konstantinopole, 1920 (Folder 11-14)
  - File 11. Information reports, bulletins, and official orders issued by VSIUR, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - File 12, 1920
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Folder 3)
    - Reports re situation in Germany received from the Russkaia Delegatsiia po Delam Voennoplennykh I Bezhentsev v Germanii (Folder 4)
    - Summaries of European and Soviet press (Folder 5)
  - File 13. Operations telegrams from the British War Office re situation on Russian fronts, 1920-1921 (Folder 6-7)
  - File 14
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with private individuals
      - 1919 (Folder 9-10)
      - 1920 (Folder 11)
    - Orders issued by VSIUR and other official communications. Includes Bainbridge Colby's note on U.S.-Russian relations (Folder 12)
  - File 15. Correspondence re care in Swiss sanatoria of sick and invalid former Russian prisoners of war and their repatriation and reports re condition, political mood, and Soviet influence on former prisoners of war. Includes correspondence of Société de la Croix-Rouge de Russie, Bureau de Secours aux Prisonniers de Guerre, Section Russe, Berne, 1919-1920 (Folder 13-14)
  - File 16. Operational, political, and intelligence reports received by the Rossiiskaia Voennaia Agentura v SHveitsarii from General D. Shcherbachev, Voennyi Predstavitel' Verkhovnago Pravitelia pri Soiuznykh Pravitel'stvakh I Soiuznom Verkhovnom Komandovanii, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - File 17. Same as above, 1919 December-1920 March (Folder 4-7)
  - File 18. Same as above, 1920 March-September (Folder 8-10)
  - File 19. Same as above, 1920 September-December (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - File 20, 1919. See also OVERSIZE FILE
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Folder 4)
    - Orders issued by British commander, Maj.-Gen. H. C. Holman to British Military Mission, South Russia (Folder 5)
    - Reports
      - Dezhurnyi General Shtaba (military court decisions) (Folder 6)
      - Morskoe Upravlenie VSIUR (complement of ships in the White fleet (Folder 7)
      - Osobaia Kommissiia po Razsledovaniiu Zlodeianii Bol'shevikov, Sostoiashchaia pri Glavnokomanduiushchem VSIUR (Folder 8)
  - File 21. Office of the Rossiiskaia Voennaia Agentura v Shveitsarii. Correspondence
    - Original binding cover describing material included in file (Folder 9)
    - Russian government agencies
      - 1918 (Folder 10)
      - 1919 (Folder 11)
      - 1920 (Folder 12)
    - Swiss officials and Allied representatives (Folder 13)
  - File 22. Bound clippings from Swiss, British, and Russian press, 1919 (Box 6-8)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1919-1920.
  Includes oversize material from File 20
  - Proclamations under signature of Lieut.-Gen. Aleksei Denikin (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Reports (operational, political, and intelligence) issued by the Shtab Glavnokomanduiushchago VSIUR
    - General (Folder 2-3)
    - Leaflets (Folder 4)